Good morning, everybody.
大家早上好
It's six o'clock on Sunday morning
现在是周日早上六点
英国广播公司电台2台开始新一天的节目播出
and the BBC Light Programme
is beginning another day's broadcast.
南北越军队在福隆县展开激烈的交火
Fierce fighting between North and
South Vietnamese troops in Phuoc Long
Province...
翻倍?
Double?
我喜欢付现 Emile
I'd sooner cash, Emile.
But I suppose I can trust you.
但我想我可以相信你
Pint, Morse?
喝一杯 Morse?
Morse
Morse.
喝一杯?
Pint?
我不喝酒
I don't drink.
- 你知道的
- 那喝杯果汁
You know that Have a squash.
- 今天Sally请客 和Charlie在一起的那个姑娘
- 我也想去 McLeash
Sally's serving. The one with the
charlies. I'd like to, McLeash.
但是...
But um...
On a Sunday?
星期日还干活?
老工作会变傻的 伙计
All work, old son...
谢谢你来叫上我 下次吧
Well, it's good of you to ask,
but another time.
上次你也是这么说的
That's what you said last time.
Lisa Bainwright?
Yes, miss.
- Lisa Bainwright?
- 到 小姐
Jenny Crisp?
Yes, miss.
- Jenny Crisp?
- 到 小姐
- Pauline Edmonds?
Pauline Edmonds?
Yes, miss.
- Valerie Quillen?
- 到 小姐
Valerie Quillen?
Yes, miss.
Anne Porter?
- Anne Porter?
- 到 小姐
Mary Tremlett?
Is Mary not in today?
Mary今天没来吗?
Has anybody seen her?
有人见过她吗?
我听说Crisp的女儿在这上学
Crisp's daughter goes here, I heard.
I wouldn't know.
Any word on those extra bodies?
我不知道
Request has gone in for
reinforcements from Carshall.
Due first thing tomorrow.
增援人手方面有消息吗?
从Carshall来的增援人员明天一早就到
'Mary Tremlett aged 15,
left home on Saturday
Mary Tremlett 15岁 星期六下午四点左右离家
at approximately four
o'clock in the afternoon
for a trip to the cinema.
去看电影
最后一次见到时 身着橙色上衣
Last seen wearing an orange top,
绿色时尚七分裤
green three-quarter-length
trousers in a fashionable
至今尚无音信
Capri pants style, she
has not been seen since.
Anyone with information
pertaining to her disappearance
任何人如有关于她失踪的信息
should contact Detective
Inspector Fred Thursday
应联系牛津Cowley警局的
at Cowley Police Station, Oxford.
Fred Thursday警督
It is believed extra officers
from Carshall Newtown
据信 Carshall Newtown的增援警察
are being drafted in to assist in
the search.'
已被抽调来协助调查
这说的可是我们
Well, that's us, that is.
听说你不想来参与调查 为什么?
'Ere, what's this I heard you tried
to get yourself taken off the
inquiry?
Morse?
Morse
Wilcox Duffle Ellis Wood
你们去Banbury报道
Wilcox, Duffle, Ellis, Wood,
you're assigned to Banbury.
DS McBain.
He's waiting for you in the canteen.
McBain警长在食堂等你们
Cullen Boyle Madden Mitchell
你们去Kidlington
Cullen, Boyle, Madden, Mitchell,
Kidlington. DS Anthony.
车在院子那头
Transport's through the yard.
Hurry it up.
动作快点
Finger out of your arse.
别浪费时间
You two, follow me.
你们两个 跟我来
我估计你俩对自己都很满意是吧
I suppose you're feeling
very pleased with yourselves.
Dreaming of cracking
a great big juicy murder case, eh?
梦想破个重大谋杀案?
- 名字能上报纸?
- 是的 警长
Get your name in the papers?
Yes, sarge.
Well, you can forget it.
There's only two
得了 别妄想了
这个警局只有两个探长 我和老大
detectives in this nick:
Me and the guv'nor.
那位你们要叫他Thursday先生 或者 "长官"
And that's Mr Thursday to you. Or
'sir'.
Get in. Go on.
进去吧
你们来是好好干活的
You're here to take up slack.
还有问题吗? 没 很好
Any questions? No, good.
我以为这是个人口失踪案
I thought this was a missing persons
case.
You said murder.
你说是谋杀
Oh, it's murder all right.
Sex case like as not.
噢 是谋杀 可能是性侵犯案
办案过程和如今电视上播的差不多
The way they go round
with all on show these days.
Just not found her body yet.
只不过还没找到她的尸体
那么 工作内容
So, duties.
McLeash负责办公室 值班记录 接电话
及其他任何收到的信息
McLeash, office, duty log, telephone
calls, any and all information
received.
Sarge.
E Morse.
- 好的
- E Morse
Your guv'nor says you know the area.
你老大说你对这片挺了解
大学生
College boy.
是吧?
That right?
好了 挨家挨户去把这个发一下
Right, door to door. Get that lot
circulated.
You can't tell from those
but she's a redhead,
你从这上面看不出
但她是红头发 很成熟
well-developed for her age.
Someone would have seen her.
可能有人见过她
Shops, offices, railways,
commuters... Commuters?
- 商店 办公室 火车站 上下班的人
- 上下班的人?
If she left Oxford by train on
Saturday afternoon,
如果她星期六下午坐火车离开牛津的话
上下班的人不可能见到她 你不这么认为吗?
it's unlikely she'd have been seen
by the weekday crowd, wouldn't you
think?
我不认为 我只执行命令
Well, I don't think. I follow orders.
Anyone want me, I'm with the guv'nor.
如果有人要找我的话 我在老大那儿
Kept that under your hat, didn't
you?
你会保密是吧?
Bloody Oxford.
他妈的牛津
伊比库斯除了他的诗
最广为人知的也许是
His verse notwithstanding, Ibycus is
perhaps most famous for the manner of
his death
at the hands of robbers.
他死在强盗的手上
Wounded and dying, Ibycus looked up
to see a flight of crane...
受伤临死之即 伊比库斯抬头看到一群鹤
A flight of cranes passing overhead.
一群鹤飞过头顶
At which he cried out,
'Those birds will be my avengers.'
他大声喊到 "这些鸟会成为我的复仇者"
Plutarch说 那些谋害他的凶手
His murderers repaired to Corinth,
去往Corinth 在那里
where, Plutarch tells us,
spying a flock of the same birds,
那群强盗看到了一群鹤
one of their number exclaimed in
jest,
其中一位开玩笑地大喊
"看呐 伊比库斯的复仇者"
'Behold, the avengers of Ibycus.'
卫生间在二楼 可以洗澡
Bathroom's on the first
landing for proper washing.
But you've a sink up here for
shaving
但是这里有个水槽 可以刮胡子
该有的都有了
and the necessary's where it should
be.
- 第一次来牛津?
- 不是
First time in Oxford?
Not exactly.
那很好 亲爱的
Well, that's nice, dear, isn't it?
这是Bleaney先生的房间
This was Mr Bleaney's room.
He stayed here the whole time
he was at the Bodleian.
他在牛津图书馆的时候 一直住在这
你知道你会在这住多久吗
Do you know how long you'll be in
residence? I'm afraid not.
No, well, it's just yourself
and two other gentlemen at the
minute.
不知道 好吧 现在这里住着你和另外两位先生
Mr Goldberg and Mr McCann.
Goldberg先生和McCann先生
Very nice, they are.
他们人很好
晚饭每天6点半开始
Tea's at 6:30 as a rule.
但是我可以现在给你煮个鸡蛋
But I can do you a boiled egg.
Oh, that's very kind of you, Mrs
Crabbin, but I'll get something out.
噢 非常感谢 Crabbin太太
但是我出去吃
那你先安顿一下吧
Then I'll let you get settled.
There's no overtime.
加班没加班费的
我知道
I realise that
So what is it, brown-nosing
or sucker for punishment?
那这是拍马屁还是自我惩罚?
There's no other kind of bloody fool
still in the office at this time of
night.
不然没有哪个傻子
这么晚还待在办公室
Just us.
我们就会
我觉得我该看一下Tremlett的案件卷宗
I thought I should take a look at
the Tremlett case files.
你是哪个? Morse 长官
Which one are you?
Morse, sir.
Carshall Newtown.
Carshall Newtown来的
看出什么?
So?
Mary Tremlett 15岁 星期六下午4点离家
Mary Tremlett 15 years old,
最后见她的是她父母
可能跟另外一个叫Valerie的女孩去看电影了
Last seen by her parents Saturday
four o'clock when she left,
supposedly to go to the pictures
with another girl, Valerie.
- 叫Valerie...
- Quillen
但她否认了这件事
Valerie...
Quillen.
没有男朋友
Who denies any such arrangement.
No boyfriend.
家庭和睦
No troubles at home.
So it's unlikely she's a runaway.
所以不像是离家出走
就这些
That's it.
Not much to go on.
没什么新发现
There rarely is, this kind of case.
这类案子一般都线索比较少
但我们还是得努力破案
But we keep looking.
Good night, then.
晚安
有一件事 长官
There is one thing, sir.
我看了下她家中所有物的清单
Going through this list
of her belongings at home...
She's a copy of The Oxford Book Of
English Verse by her bed,
她床头有本牛津英语诗集
together with A Shropshire Lad
and a Betjeman Collected.
还有什罗普郡一少年和本杰明全集
Young girls like poetry.
年轻女孩喜欢诗
像Mary Tremlett这样的年轻女孩?
Young girls like Mary Tremlett?
Too highbrow for a girl whose father
works on the GMC assembly line? That
your point?
你是说 她父亲在通用汽车流水线工作
所以她学识太高?
不 我的意思是它们都是精装本
No, my point is that they're
hardbacks.
Beyond the pocket of a schoolgirl,
I'd have thought.
我觉得女学生是负担不起的
只是让我觉得很奇怪 就这样
Just struck me as odd, that's all.
也许它们是份礼物 她父母给的 说不定是学校奖励
Maybe they were a present.
Her parents, a school prize even.
There's official lines of inquiry
we're following, Morse.
调查还是得按部就班来 Morse
Poetry books isn't one of them.
查诗集不是其中之一
Is Mary fond of poetry, Mr Tremlett?
Tremlett先生 Mary喜欢诗词吗?
She's nice handwriting.
她写字很漂亮
The teachers commended her on it.
老师表扬过她
A-plus last report.
上次给了她A加
Sharon, my eldest, she's visiting.
Sharon 我大女儿 她来探望我
这是警察
Police.
How do you do, Miss Tremlett?
你好 Tremlett小姐
Mrs. Veelie.
Veelie太太
They had her read out
some of her essays to the class.
他们让她在课堂上朗读她的文章
没了她这里都变了
The house isn't the same.
求你找到她好吗
Find her, will you, please?
找到我们的Mary
Find our Mary.
你在找什么?
What is it you're looking for?
Oh, just filling in some of the
background.
了解一下基本情况
So you weren't here Saturday?
所以你星期六不在?
I dropped by the afternoon to see to
Dad's tea but I went straight home
after.
我下午过来照料爸爸的晚饭
然后我就回去了
5点左右
About five.
Where's home?
Droitwich.
- 你家在哪?
- Droitwich
我们星期日要做盘点
We had a stock-take Sunday, see.
Freeman Hardy和Willis公司
Freeman, Hardy and Willis.
I'm Deputy Under-Manageress.
我是副经理
你丈夫呢
And your husband?
他是做地毯的
He's in carpets.
Travelling.
出门了?
我们分开了
We're not together any more.
你和你妹妹关系好吗 Veelie太太?
Are you close to your sister,
Mrs Veelie?
Not really.
不太好
这些小题大作...
All this fuss...
It'll just be some stunt.
只不过是装出来
寻求关注而已
Attention seeking.
你为什么这么说?
What makes you say that?
Cos she's always been the same.
因为她一直都这样
妈妈还在世的时候 她被宠坏了
When Mum was alive, she spoilt her
rotten.
爸爸也是
Dad too.
Whatever she wanted.
要什么给什么
他们心爱的小女孩
Their blue-eyed girl.
小贱人
Silly little cow.
别这样 警察在这
The police were here.
Nobody's seen her.
没人见过她
- 你觉得她知道什么吗?
- 她怎么会知道?
Do you think she knows something?
How would she know?
Extension 255.
接分机255
Yes, I'll hold.
好的 我不挂
Morning.
早
早啊
Aye aye.
- 那是啥?
- Mary Tremlett的诗集
What you got there, then?
Mary Tremlett's poetry books.
- 干啥用?
- 我也不知道 说不定没发现
Well, what's all that about?
I don't know yet. Nothing, probably.
你该死的去哪了?
Where the bloody hell have you been?
Got a suicide in Thrupp.
Unidentified male. You're on.
Thrupp有件自杀案 无名男子 案子给你了
我要怎么过去啊?
How am I meant to get there?
Want me to wipe your arse for you
an' all?
要我手把手教你吗?
Use your initiative.
动动脑子
早
Morning.
Not for this poor sod.
这可怜的家伙可见不到了
You are whom?
你是哪位?
探员Morse
Morse. Detective Constable.
On attachment from Newtown.
Newtown派来的
我想 你是法医吧?
You're the pathologist, I presume?
还好我是是吧?
Better hope so, hadn't you?
不然你的犯罪现场可是被我搞得一团糟啊
Otherwise I'm making one hell of a
mess of your scene of crime.
Max DeBryn
Max DeBryn.
Is it a scene of crime?
这是犯罪现场吗?
初步报告表明这是自杀
Initial report suggested suicide.
看起来是 右太阳穴一个创伤进口
Looks to be. Single entry wound on
the right temple.
在伤口周围的皮肤上有典型的火药四射的痕迹
Typical starburst gunpowder pattern
on the skin surrounding the wound
还有接触灼伤
together with contact scorching
would suggest the weapon was
discharged at point-blank range.
这些都表明是在近距离平射射程开枪的
As you can see.
正如你所见
I'll take your word for it.
我相信你说的
Squeamish, are we?
恶心是吧
You won't make much of a detective
if you're not prepared to look death
in the eye.
如果你无法直面死亡的话 是无法成为探长的
你这里搞定了来找我
Find me when you're done.
RADIO: # MANFRED MANN: Do Wah Diddy
(你看到过她吗?)
搞定了?
Finished?
The hors d'oeuvres.
这只是前菜 正餐下午3点整开始
Entree this afternoon.
Three o'clock sharp.
你能打电话告诉我结果的吧?
You can give me your findings
over the telephone.
You know, there's a word for people
like you, Morse.
你知道吗 Morse
有个词可以形容你这样的人
- 是吗?
- 尸体恐惧
Is there?
Necrophobic.
我想也有个词可以形容你这样的人
A word for people like you too,
I imagine.
虽然是英国人 倒不如说是希腊人
Anglo-Saxon, though, rather than
Greek.
Weapon's a Webley, Mark VI,
if you're interested.
凶器是韦伯利左轮手枪4型
如果你想知道的话
.455, standard army issue?
子弹口径455 标准军用?
- 不笨啊?
- 当然 死亡时间?
Not entirely a fool, then?
Not entirely. Time of death?
Yesterday between eight and
midnight.
昨晚在8点到12点之间
- 他还留下点什么吗?
- 除了草皮上他的灰质之外的东西吗?
Did he leave anything behind? Beside
his grey matter upon the greensward?
- 我是指像字条之类的
- 我没看到
I was thinking more of a note.
Not that I've come across.
You might have better luck at his
lodgings. This was in his pocket.
你在他住的地方说不定会有发现
这个在他口袋里发现的
Miles Percival.
Address is in Jericho.
他叫Miles Percival 住在Jericho
I don't suppose there's any chance of
a lift?
捎我一程没问题吧?
Detective Constable Morse.
探员Morse
牛津郡警察
Oxford City Police.
- Mr...?
- Lomax.
- 你贵姓?
- Lomax
Brian Lomax.
Brian Lomax
Miles Percival是住在这里吗?
Would I be right in thinking
Miles Percival lives here?
When? I mean, where?
什么时候? 在哪?
昨晚
Last night.
His body was found down by the river
at Thrupp this morning.
他的尸体今早在Thrupp的河边被人发现
Had you known him long?
Two years.
- 你认识他多久?
- 两年
We sang together in the choir
for a bit.
我们在合唱班一起合唱过
When did you see him last?
你最后见他是什么时候
昨天 在学校
Yesterday, at college.
他看上去怎么样
How did he seem?
Anything worrying him?
他有担心什么事吗?
No.
没有
那最近呢
What about recently?
有什么反常吗?
Anything out of the ordinary?
Money problems? College?
Girl trouble?
金钱问题? 学校问题? 男女问题?
Nothing he told me about.
他没和我说过
- 你是澳大利亚人 Lomax先生?
- 是的
You're Australian, Mr Lomax.
That's right.
From where?
Sydney.
- 澳大利亚哪?
- 悉尼
And you weren't concerned
that he didn't come home last night?
所以他昨晚没回家 你一点都没担心
Well, I was in the Bird till
closing.
昨天我在Bird酒吧待到关门
我回来的时候 以为他已经回来了
When I got back,
I thought he'd already turned in.
Did you know he owned a gun?
你知道他有枪吗?
His grandfather's.
他祖父的
I'll need to speak to his tutor.
Sure.
我要和他的老师谈谈 好
He teaches over at Lonsdale.
他老师在Lonsdale学院
Morse...
Morse
Morse.
Good God.
Hello, Alex.
- 老天
- 你好 Alex
简直不敢相信啊 你在这干什么呢
I don't believe it.
What the hell are you doing here?
我来找一位你的同事 Stromming博士
I'm looking for a colleague of
yours. Dr Stromming.
找他何事?
What's your business with him?
警务 我是警察
Police business. I'm a policeman.
Police?
警察?
The last I heard, you'd run off to
join the Foreign Legion.
最近一次听到你的消息是你要加入外籍兵团
怎么了? 没选上?
What happened? Didn't take?
皇家通讯兵团
It was the Royal Signals.
But, no, 'didn't take'.
但是 我没去
You're still...
Climbing the ladder of academe?
- 你还在...
- 攀爬学术院的阶梯?
噢 是的
Oh, yes.
All the way to the top-most rung.
自始至终都在最前列
Master, one day, I suppose.
我想 有天能爬到校长吧
- 你一直都这么有野心
- 天才做必做之事
Well, you always were ambitious.
Genius does what it must.
- 边走边说 我午餐迟到了
- 不行
Walk with me. I'm late for lunch.
I can't.
You won't find Stromming in today.
Home, probably.
Stromming今天不在 大概是在家
Porter'll give you the address.
门房会给你地址的
One must marry well, you see?
你知道吗 结婚要结的好
More than the half of it here
if you want to get on.
在这就等于成功了一大半 如果你想成功的话
你成家了吗?
You taken the plunge?
- 还没
- 没啊
Not yet.
No.
What was the name of that girl
we were keen on? Lived on St John
Street.
我们都喜欢的那个姑娘叫什么?
住在St John街的
- Wendy是吧?
- 她喜欢别人叫她Susan
Wendy, was it?
Susan. She preferred Susan.
是吗? 真的?
Did she? Did she?
And you to me, as I recall.
而且更喜欢你 我没记错的话
不过世事公平...
Still, all's fair...
Well, I oughtn't keep you from
your...
好了 我不应该占用你时间的
But good to see you, Morse.
Very good.
但是很高兴见到你 Morse 非常高兴
A word of advice. As an old friend.
作为老朋友 给你个忠告
Whatever it is you're about in
college, mind how you go.
不管你在学院里要干什么 小心你的举止
They won't take kindly to an
interloper.
他们对外来人员可不和善
Particularly one of their own.
I'm not sure I was ever that.
特别对曾是他们一分子的人 我可不确定我曾是他们的人
No.
你不是
Well, dig me out.
We'll have supper. Proper catch-up.
好了 记得找我 一起吃晚饭 好好聚一聚
Ah, good afternoon.
I'm looking for Dr Stromming.
下午好 我找Stromming博士
抱歉 他出去了
Oh, I'm sorry. He's out at present.
Is it college business?
是学院里的事吗?
算是吧
In a manner of speaking.
Do you have any idea what time he'll
be back? No, I'm afraid not.
- 你知道他什么时候回来吗?
- 不 我不知道
Can I take a message?
我可以帮你带个口信吗?
It's probably best if I speak to him
directly.
我还是直接和他说比较合适
好吧
I see.
- 那...
- 好 那我...
Well...
Yes, um, I'll...
Sorry to have troubled you.
很抱歉打扰你
Not at all.
没有的事
请原谅我的冒昧 你是Calloway小姐吧?
Forgive me but it is Miss Calloway,
isn't it?
Rosalind Calloway小姐?
Miss Rosalind Calloway?
It was. It's Mrs Stromming now.
以前是 现在是Stromming太太
Ah...
那个
我不能说我全都收齐了
Well, I can't say I've all,
but I've very many of your
recordings, certainly.
但是我有很多很多你的唱片 真的
Good heavens.
老天
是的 54年你的蝴蝶夫人
Yeah, your Butterfly in '54.
如果我上荒岛唱片的话 我一定会选择带这个
If I had to save one disc on my
desert island from the waves, that
would...
You are very kind.
你太客气了
Well...
Look, I'm sure Rowan won't be long.
- 呃...
- 你看 我想Rowan一会就会回来
你要不要...
Would you, um...
你要不要留下来等他?
Would you care to wait?
You don't miss it, performing?
你不怀念表演的时光吗
Not for a moment.
不会
你知道 我有Rowan了 我先生
You see, I've got Rowan. My husband.
It seemed like more than a fair
exchange.
可不止是公平交换
The one didn't preclude the other,
surely?
两者真的不会互相冲突吗?
Well, not for Rowan's part.
和Rowan一起不会
而和音乐结婚 却不是我想要的婚姻
For mine, it's not the kind of
marriage that I wanted.
巡演
Touring. Oceans apart.
远隔重洋
Forsaking all others, certainly,
but... music.
放弃其他的当然可以理解 但...音乐
No, I still have music.
I help out with the college choir
on Wednesdays and Saturdays.
不 我依旧拥有音乐
我周三和周六会去学院合唱团帮忙
And, oh, I have agreed to appear
in a charity gala at the New next
Monday.
而且 我还答应下周一在New剧院做慈善晚会
To be honest,
I think I'm more nervous about this
老实说 我对这次表演特别紧张
比以前任何一次表演都紧张
than any other performance I have
ever given.
还有票吗?
Are tickets still available?
他们告诉我票卖完了 那当然
All gone, I'm told.
Of course.
Rowan. This is Mr...
Rowan 这位是...
Morse.
Morse
He's come to talk with you.
他是来找你的
- 学院里的事
- 好的
College business.
Yes, of course.
你确定你不要来一杯?
Are you sure you won't have one?
Um, no, thank you.
不 谢谢
请坐
Please.
我有什么可以帮你的吗 Morse先生
So, what can I do for you, Mr Morse?
Actually, Doctor, it's Detective
Constable Morse.
其实我是探员Morse 博士
牛津郡警察
Oxford City Police.
I'm here about a student of yours.
Miles Percival.
我来是因为你的一位学生 Miles Percival
噢 怎么了?
Oh, yes?
我很抱歉告诉你这件事
但是今天早上发现他死了
I'm sorry to have to tell you, sir,
but I'm afraid he was found dead this
morning.
死了
Dead?
Oh, my God.
噢 我的天
How awful.
这太糟了
What was it, a car accident or
something?
怎么会的 交通意外还是什么?
我们认为他是自杀
We believe he killed himself.
Have you any idea why he may wish to
take his own life?
你知道他为什么要自杀吗?
None.
不知道
他最近学习有点脱节
His work had fallen off quite badly
of late.
缺课 喝醉
Missed tutorials. Drinking.
There was some talk of him being
rusticated.
有闲话说他太土
他挺容易过激
He was quite highly-strung.
But I had no idea he was in that
kind of...
但是我不知道他会那么...
老天 可怜的孩子
My God, the poor boy.
I need a name and address
for your Saturday puzzle-setter. Oz.
我需要你们周六纵横字谜出题人Oz的姓名和地址
真可惜 他是匿名的
Out of luck, then, aren't you. He's
anonymous.
Like most of them.
就和大多数人一样
Well, you send his fee somewhere,
presumably.
你总得把稿费寄给他吧
Fee?
稿费?
这是牛津 他们出题为的是荣誉
This is Oxford. They do it for the
honour.
Look, I really am fearfully busy.
I've got the stars to do by lunch.
听着 我现在很忙 午饭前我得把星座都搞定
我才刚做到金牛座
I'm only at Taurus.
人们不会真信这些东西吧?
People don't really believe such
guff, do they?
这可不一定 基督教堂的牧师刚宣布轮回呢
You'd be surprised. The chaplain at
Christ's has just declared for
reincarnation.
When's it usually delivered?
平时是什么时候寄来的?
星期六的字谜
The Saturday grid.
通常星期三一早送来
First post Wednesday as a rule.
We go to press Thursday.
我们星期四要印刷
那上周呢?
And last week?
真是个好问题
Funny you should ask.
Came in late. Caused quite a flap.
送晚了 惹了不少麻烦
In the end a young chap dropped it
round...
后来是个年轻人送来的
Well, what did he look like?
他长什么样?
年轻人样
Like a young chap.
本科生 我猜
Undergrad, I suppose.
Gave it to one of the subs. I caught
a glimpse.
手下员工收的 我就扫了眼
Well, perhaps I could speak to this
sub.
那我也许该和这位员工谈谈
You'll have to scour the Cairngorms,
I'm afraid. Walking holiday as of
Monday.
那我恐怕你得搜索下Cairngorms山了
因为这星期一开始徒步旅行假期
好吧
Very well.
Well, if you remember anything
else... Of course.
- 如果你还想起来什么的话...
- 当然
谢谢
Thank you.
What did you say your name was?
你刚才说你叫什么?
Morse
Morse.
- 怎么?
- 我们见过吗?
Why?
Have we met?
I don't think so.
没有
Another life, then.
那另一个人生见吧
喂 Lott请病假
Oi, Lott's rung in sick.
换你去接老大
You're to fetch the guv'nor.
我怎么过去?
How am I supposed to get there?
No DS Lott today?
Unwell, sir.
- Lott警长今天没来?
- 病假 长官
未必
You don't say.
今天星期五 肯定是咸碎牛肉
Now, Friday, must be corned beef.
Ah, what did I tell you?
我说对了吧?
说到可靠
When it comes to reliability,
the fixed motion
of the heavens has
nothing on my woman.
我老婆可真是多少年如一日啊
昨天晚上可有新发现?
Anything overnight?
There is something I wanted to talk
to you about.
事实上我的确有发现要和你说 长官
Mary Tremlett's poetry books.
I thought we'd been through that.
- Mary Tremlett的诗集
- 我以为我们已经讨论过这问题了
我知道 但它们不仅是精装本 长官
它们还是初版 很贵重
I know, but they're not just
hardbacks, sir, they're first
editions. Quite valuable.
你怎么... 你去过她家
How do you...? You've been there.
好吧 路上说
Right, tell me on the way.
Morning, sir.
Morning.
- 早 长官
- 早
Just bringing Mr Crisp up to date,
sir.
刚给Crisp先生汇报了最新进展 长官
是吗? 我以为你病了
You were, were you?
I thought you were sick.
- 早上略有不适
- 没想到啊
A bit liverish first thing.
Fancy.
好了Morse 去做你的事吧
OK, Morse, back to your desk.
等等 Arthur
Wait a minute, Arthur.
See what you make of this, sir.
The lad's been having a bit of a dig
round the Tremlett case.
你听听他的发现 长官 这孩子对Tremlett的案子做了点深入研究
Tell him.
说吧
Mary Tremlett keeps a few poetry
books by her bed. First editions.
Mary Tremlett在她床头有好些诗集 初版的
And she's bookmarked certain poems
with crosswords cut from the Oxford
Mail.
她拿牛津日报的纵横字谜
当某些诗的书签
周六版牛津日报 这些字谜都是一个叫Oz的人出的
The Saturday edition.
All set by someone called Oz.
Oz? As in the Wizard of?
- Oz?
- 绿野仙踪的Oz?
Well, the same spelling, yes.
相同的拼写 是的
Um, but the thing is, there's only
ever two clues she's filled in any
puzzle.
但问题是她每次只完成两条字谜
同样位置的两条
横向第一个和纵向最后一个
The same two.
The first across and the last down.
The down's invariably a number.
纵向的是各种数字
Five gold rings, six geese a-laying,
so on.
五只金戒指 六只生蛋的鹅 等等
但是横向提示始终是诗里提到的
But the across clue always refers to
somewhere in or around Oxford
牛津或附近某地地名
mentioned in the poems.
Fyfield Cumnor Godstow
Fyfield, Cumnor, Godstow.
- 就这样?
- 不 长官 还有
That it?
No, sir, not quite.
她失踪这天的纵横字谜
The crossword that came out
the day she disappeared
提到了马修·阿诺德的诗
refers to a poem by Matthew Arnold,
The Scholar Gipsy,
吉卜赛学者
其中提到了Bagley Wood
which mentions Bagley Wood.
Bagley Wood?
纵向提示是数字八
The down clue gives the number
eight.
I just thought it could be a time.
我只是觉得这可能是时间
和地点
And place.
可能
Possibly.
You think someone's making
secret assignations with her?
你觉得有人利用牛津日报
Through crossword clues in the
Oxford Mail?
用纵横字谜提示和她秘密见面
Extraordinary, isn't it?
That's one word for it.
- 很棒是吧
- 这只是一面之词
抱歉长官 但我从没听说过这么胡扯的
Begging your pardon, sir, but I've
never heard so much codswallop.
这听起来有点不真实 甚至有点牵强
It does seem a bit fanciful,
far-fetched even.
Bagley Wood! Have you signed off
on that Thrupp shooting yet?
Bagley Wood 你Thrupp的射杀案签了没?
那我建议你闲逛前先把事情做完
Then I suggest you see to your
duties before you start
gallivanting.
Bloody crosswords!
搞什么纵横字谜
信息科来消息 长官
有路人发现了一具尸体
Just come through from the
information room, sir. A body's been
found by ramblers.
一个年轻姑娘 红发
看起来应该是Mary Tremlett
A young girl, redhead.
Looks to be Mary Tremlett.
Where's this?
在哪?
Kennington, out by Bagley Wood.
Kennington 在Bagley Wood郊外
让摄影师一定要照到这个
Make sure the photographer gets
this.
她的右手背
Back of her right hand.
它已经被弄脏了
It's already smudged.
看上去是FLA17...
It looks to be FLA17...
什么的
something.
可能是字母B
Letter B, possibly.
车牌?
Car registration?
Or flat, maybe? Flat 17B?
也可能是门牌? 房间17B?
Then what? Post-mortem?
然后呢? 尸检?
先做正式身份辨认 Morse可以载我
Formal identification first.
Morse can run me.
你最好在这盯着搜查
You'd better keep an eye on the
search.
Organise a few snaps of her outfit
before it goes for forensics.
她的外套送去鉴证科前先多照几张相
Get them out there.
散发出去
It might jog a few memories.
Very good, sir.
- 说不定会有发现
- 好的 长官
谁是聪明人来着?
Who's a clever boy, then?
Sarge.
警长
这里
Over here.
死者为女性 营养良好
The subject is a well-nourished
female.
Approximately 15 years of age.
年龄约15岁
Five foot two.
身高五尺二寸
体重9石6磅
Nine stone six pounds.
So, we begin with a lateral
incision...
好了 我们沿着头盖骨
侧切
across the cranium.
Peel the scalp forward,
剥开头皮
因此头骨可见
thus to expose the skull.
Morse... Morse!
你会没事的
You'll be all right.
实际上 长官 我不喝酒
Actually, sir, I don't drink.
非常值得表扬 现在把它喝了
Very commendable. Now, get that down
you.
如果你要道歉 就不必了
If you're going to apologise, don't.
Your first?
Well, like that.
- 你第一次?
- 像这样是第一次
North Africa was mine.
北非是我的第一次
Long Stop Hill.
在Long Stop Hill
一个叫Mills的孩子
A lad by the name of Mills.
Gunner Mills.
炮手Mills
Not a mark on him.
身上没什么异样
我以为他睡着了
I thought he was asleep.
Till I turned him over.
直到我把他翻过身来
迫击炮
Mortar.
- 我错过了什么?
- 勒死
What did I miss?
Strangled.
Her own brassiere.
用的是她自己内衣肩带
面朝地从后勒死的
Struck on the back of the head first.
据DeBryn医生所说 无性侵犯迹象
Hadn't been interfered with,
according to Dr DeBryn.
Then why take off her clothes?
那为什么要脱了她衣服呢
说不定本来想的
Maybe the spirit was willing...
星期六晚上 喝多了 想实施侵犯
Saturday night, he'd had a skinful,
tried to have his way.
When he couldn't manage it...
结果无法得逞
She'd been pregnant at some point
within the last six months.
在过去的六个月里 她曾有过身孕
Very professional job
was the doctor's opinion.
根据医生的观点 堕胎做得很利落
- 所以她是有男朋友的?
- 我们的Oz?
So there was a boyfriend?
Our man Oz?
搜寻发现在她尸体的附近 有一只男性手表
The search turned up a gent's
wristwatch near where her body was
found.
表面被砸了 所以我们有死亡时间
The face is smashed,
which gives us a time of death.
8:16 Saturday night.
周六晚 8点16分
还有 她的胃里有半品脱的海螺
Oh, and her stomach contents
turned up half a pint of whelks.
和她的朋友Valerie聊聊
Talk to her mate Valerie.
See if she's been holding back.
看她是否隐瞒了什么
她说不定会乐意向同龄人开口
She might open up more
to someone nearer her own age.
Right.
好
Mary Tremlett告诉她父亲 星期六下午
Mary Tremlett told her father
she was going to the cinema with you
她和你去电影院
Saturday afternoon.
Any idea why she'd say that?
你知道她为什么要这样说吗
I can understand if you've been
wanting to... protect her.
我知道你想保护她
比如她的名节
Maybe her reputation.
But as of this morning,
things have changed.
但是从今天早上起 事情已经变了
For the worse, I'm afraid.
变糟了
Are you saying she's dead?
你是说她死了?
So it's important you tell me
the truth. Now. Do you understand?
所以告诉我真相是非常重要的 你明白吗?
Where was she going Saturday night?
她星期六晚上去哪了
她去见谁?
Who was she seeing?
我不知道
I don't know.
我要回家
Look, I want to go home.
I'm upset. I've had a shock.
我难过 我太震惊了
我难过的时候不想和人说话
You can't talk to me when I'm upset.
你是为了Mary的事来的吗?
Are you here about Mary?
We were best friends before she fell
in with Valerie's crowd.
以前我们是好朋友 后来她和Valerie那群人好了
- 你和她们不是一起的?
- 不是 一群小荡妇
You're not part of that?
No fear. Little tarts.
They used to rag on us when we first
started.
我们刚开始的时候 她们常常骂我们
Only, last year Mary and Val got
really pally.
去年开始 Mary和Val走得很近
And then a couple of weeks ago
they had a big bust-up.
然后几周前 她们大吵了一架
Do you know what it was about?
你知道是为什么吗?
Mary thought Valerie
was trying to steal her bloke.
Mary觉得Valerie要抢她的男人
她们为这个吵的
They had a fight over it.
Did Mary ever mention anyone called
Oz?
Mary提过一个叫Oz的人吗
A nickname, maybe.
可能是外号
没和我提过
Not to me.
And who's Mary's boyfriend?
那Mary的男朋友是谁
Johnny Franks
Johnny Franks. He's a car mechanic.
他是汽车维修工 在Park Town那的修车厂工作
Works at a garage over at Park Town.
All Valerie's gang go there.
Valerie那群人都去那
她可美了 是吧
She's an absolute beauty, isn't she?
Nine months old, three thousand on
the clock and does she go.
9个月的车 跑了3000英里
- Samuels先生?
- 是的 叫我Teddy
Mr Samuels?
Yeah. Call me Teddy.
- 就可以了 你是...
- 探员Morse 郡警察
Please. Mr... Detective Constable
Morse, City Police.
Oh, yeah? What can I do for you?
噢 是吗 有什么事吗?
I'd like to speak with one of your
mechanics. Johnny Franks.
我想和你的一位修车师傅聊聊 Johnny Franks
他没惹麻烦吧? 我认识很多你们局里的人
He's not in any trouble, is he?
I know a lot of your boys.
They'll tell you, I run a straight go
and I make sure my lads do the same.
他们会告诉你 我正经做人
我也确保我的手下和我一样
Right, you'd better come through.
你先进来吧
Have you seen Johnny?
你见过Johnny吗
Where were you Saturday night,
Mr Franks?
星期六晚上你在哪 Franks先生
Didcot的Railway Arms酒吧
Railway Arms in Didcot.
- 有人可以给你做证吗?
- 有 其他队员
Anyone vouch for you?
Yeah. The rest of the team.
我参加飞镖联赛 星期六在Didcot
Darts. I play in the league.
We were away to Didcot on Saturday.
What time did that finish?
Er, 11-ish.
你们什么时候结束的 呃 11点左右
I suppose I got home around midnight.
我想我到家的时候差不多12点
- 还有事吗?
- 是的
Right, then?
Not quite.
我知道你认识Mary Tremlett?
I understand you knew Mary Tremlett?
Yeah, slightly.
是的 但不熟
不止不熟吧
It was more than slightly,
wasn't it?
You were her boyfriend.
你是她男朋友
我不知道你哪听来的
I don't know where you
got that I've a few
我的确有很多女人 但Mary不在其中
birds on the go but Mary
weren't one of them.
I mean, I might have given her some
old chat but that's as far as it
went.
也就跟她聊过几句吧
那Valerie Quillen呢?
What about Valerie Quillen?
What about her?
她怎么?
Well, she had a fight with Mary.
她和Mary前几周
Over you. The other week.
因为你吵了一架
我怎么会知道这事
I wouldn't know about that
A lot of young girls hang around the
garages.
车库附近有很多年轻姑娘
You know what they're like at that
age. Lad-mad.
你知道的 她们这年纪 思春
They get an idea in their head,
what can you do?
她们胡思乱想 你能怎么办呢
Mary did have a boyfriend, as it
goes, but it weren't me.
Mary的确有男朋友 但是不是我
叫Miles什么的 大学生 名字开头是个P
Miles something.
College sort beginning with a P.
Miles Percival?
That's it. Miles Percival.
- Miles Percival?
- 是的 Miles Percival
如果你想知道Mary的事 你该去找他
You want to know about Mary,
you should go talk to him.
Mary broke it off with Miles
six months ago.
Mary6个月之前和Miles分手了
Was he sleeping with her?
What sort of a question is that?
她和他发生过关系吗? 这是什么问题?
She was 15.
她只有15岁
He wanted to marry her, for God's
sake.
老天 他想和她结婚的
他说他要为她守身
Said he was saving himself.
Miles Percival喜欢纵横字谜吗 Lomax先生
Was Miles Percival keen on
crosswords, Mr Lomax?
Miles?
Yeah.
- Miles?
- 是的
God, no. No, couldn't stick a
crossie at any price.
天啊 完全不 一点都没兴趣
没那个头脑
Didn't have that kind of mind.
我以前常把他给逼疯了
I used to drive him nuts.
You did?
是吗?
Hey, look, you've no idea what he
was like. It was awful.
嘿 听着 你不知道他是什么样的人 他很可怕
她离开他后 他不是喝酒就是...
After she left him, he was either
drunk or...
In the end, he got it into his
head...
后来 他老是觉得...
that she was seeing someone else.
她在和别人约会
他说过是谁吗?
Did he say who?
He thought that I...?
他觉得我...
It's absurd.
这真好笑
You did know her, though?
Miles brought her to a drinks party.
但是你认识她吧? Miles带她来过酒会
She seemed very personable.
Very quick-witted.
她看上去很漂亮 很机智
Really, it was just one of those
stupid things.
真的 就是有人犯傻了
One of the younger dons mentioned
有个年轻的教师说
真可惜牛津这样的姑娘太少了
it was a pity we didn't see more
people like that coming to Oxford.
Like what?
哪样的?
Well, of her class.
像她这样美丽机智的
The wine was in, I suppose, but...
大概酒喝多了
Reece hit upon a wheeze to see if,
with a bit of coaching,
Reece突发奇想 想在对她进行一番指导后
we couldn't convince the bursar
that she was an undergrad.
看是否能说服财务主管说她是本科生
Lady Matilda学院的? 你知道吗?
At Lady Matilda's. Do you see?
Alexander Reece?
Mm. Why? Do you know him?
- Alexander Reece?
- 怎么 你认识他?
Yes.
是的
如果财务主管听到是普通居民
Would have scared the
bursar half to death
而不是学术人员在讨论Pindar单韵律诗的
to hear the finer points of
Pindar's monostrophic odes
discussed in an accent
rather more town than gown.
微妙之处 会吓死的
他吓到了吗?
And was he?
Scared half to death.
他吓得半死
No, in the event the opportunity
never arose.
没 没机会实施
你们没法骗Mary Tremlett加入你们的诡计
You couldn't inveigle Mary Tremlett
to join your subterfuge.
On the cobtrary, she was all for it.
相反 她很同意加入
Someone taking an interest in her.
我想她感到高兴吧
I imagine she was flattered.
因为有人对她感兴趣
I imagine she was.
我想她是吧
Now, if you've any more questions,
you'll have to put them to me on the
hoof.
好了 如果你还有问题的话
你就只能和我边走边聊了
你最后一次见到Mary是什么时候?
When did you last see Mary?
今年早些时候 你给她做辅导?
Sometime earlier in the year.
When you were tutoring her?
一周一次 两周一次 这样
Once a week, once a fortnight,
something like that
下课后在家 她有时间的时候
After lectures, at home.
A case of when one could fit her in.
既然你认识Mary 那我得问你周六晚你在哪
Since you knew Mary, I'm bound to
ask where you were Saturday night.
I was at home.
我在家
Anyone confirm that?
My wife.
- 有人可以证明吗?
- 我太太
你太太星期六晚上不是要去合唱团练唱吗?
Your wife has choir practice
on a Saturday evening, doesn't she?
Look, whatever Miles Percival
may have thought,
听着 不管Miles Percival有什么想法
my relationship with Mary Tremlett
was based wholly on an academic
experiment.
我和Mary Tremlett的关系
都完全是建立在学术上的
Did she prove an apt pupil,
Dr Stromming?
她是个聪明的学生吗 Stromming博士?
她能靠着死记硬背来装装样子
She had a facility for conning by
rote.
但是过一阵子 那些原本会让人
But I'm afraid, after
a while, what had in
one's cups seemed amusing
no longer felt...
觉得有趣的东西就感觉
呃 没意思了
well, quite right.
Alex?
Oh, I say, full marks. You timed that
one rather well, didn't you?
你时间选得真好啊
Scoff, and a bloody good claret or
two, of course.
去吃饭吧 再来一两瓶红酒
Free and gratis.
完全免费
噢 不用了...
Oh, if it's all the same...
On duty, I suppose?
还在值勤吧?
有件事我想和你谈谈
There's something I need to talk to
you about.
Mary Tremlett 你和Rowan Stromming打的赌
Mary Tremlett. This bet that you've
got with Rowan Stromming.
Ah, I see.
啊 我知道了
Donald
Donald.
Yes, I was wondering why you were
creeping about in college.
是啊 我还在想你为什么在学院里出没
他们有更进一步的关系吗?
Anything more to their relationship?
Aside from this bet.
I wouldn't have thought so.
除了这个赌
我不这么认为 身材是不错 但对我来说太过丰乳肥臀了
Filled a sweater well enough
but a mite odalisque to my taste.
我猜薯条吃太多了
Tout avec frites, I suppose.
把那姑娘带去Cowley的郊外的话...
Take the girl out of Cowley...
你以前不是这么冷酷的
You didn't use to be so cruel.
Poor old Morse.
可怜的老伙计
You were never Oxford material.
你从来就不是牛津的料
Too bloody decent, by half.
人太好了
Abingdon 4185.
Abingdon 4185
是的
Yes.
Yes, I have.
是的 我看了
让人震惊啊
Shocking.
没有
No.
Well, I think that's wise.
我觉得那样挺聪明的
Listen, I'm just about to leave for
London.
听着 我正要去伦敦
You can reach me there if there's
anything you think I should know.
你可以去那接我 把我要知道的信息告诉我
Flaxman 1788.
FLAxman 1788
好吗?
All right?
'That the involvement of
British forces in the crisis remained
unlikely.
英国军队参与到危机中的可能性很小
同时有报道表明南北越军队在东帅市
Meanwhile, there are reports
of fighting between
South and North Vietnamese
troops in Dong Xoai.
发生交火
In other news, an early handwritten
draft of Ozymandias
其他消息 诗人珀西·比希·雪莱的
一份早期Ozymandias手稿
by the poet Percy Bysshe Shelley
即将在牛津的Bodleian图书馆展出
is to go on show
at the Bodleian Library in Oxford.
Gifted to the library in 18...'
1896年赠送给该馆...
Boundless and bare, the lone and
level sands stretch far away.
"...苍茫 荒凉 寂寥的平沙伸向远方"
Morse探员
Detective Constable Morse.
有什么事吗?
What brings you here?
I met a traveller from an antique
land
我遇到一位来自古老国度的旅者
Who said: Two vast and trunkless
legs of stone
他说 有两条巨型石腿
立于沙漠
Stand in the desert...
石腿的基座上凿刻有这样的字迹
And on the pedestal these words
appear:
"我乃Ozymandias 王中之王也
'My name is Ozymandias,
king of kings:
Look on my works, ye Mighty,
and despair!'
功业盖世 也定会颓然而绝"
- 我不明白...
- 我想你明白 Stromming博士
I'm afraid I don't...
Oh, I think you do, Dr Stromming.
Or would you prefer 'Oz'?
还是你想要我叫你"Oz"?
Ozymandias.
Ozymandias
"功业盖世 也定会颓然而绝???"
'Look on my works, ye Mighty,
and despair!'
但为了安全起见 谜面没有使用整句诗
But then crossword-setters aren't
exactly famed
for a lack of self-regard.
The gentle teacher bestowing wisdom
upon the young and eager pupil.
温柔的老师利用年轻热切的学生
It may even have started out that
way.
说不定开始是这样的
但是结局并非如此 是吧?
But it's not how it ended up. Is it?
这是怎么回事 Stromming博士
What happened, Dr Stromming?
玩腻了就甩了?
Did you tire of her just as quickly
once the shine was off it?
Or was your wife getting suspicious?
Rosalind had no idea...
- 还是你太太开始怀疑你?
- Rosalind不知道这事
Mary是不是威胁要告诉她 是这样吗?
Did Mary threaten to tell her, then,
is that it?
因为她不肯息事宁人
所以你就把她骗到Bagley Wood 是吗?
She wouldn't go quietly. Is that why
you lured her to Bagley Wood?
What?
什么
It's here, Doctor, in black and
white.
在这写着 博士 白纸黑字
第一行 "大多数吉普赛人在哪里搭帐篷"
First across: 'Where
most the Gypsies by the
答案 6和4 Bagley Wood
turf-edg'd way pitch
their smok'd tents.'
Answer, six and four: Bagley Wood.
最后一列 有多少个女牛仔
Last down, how many cowgirls?
5个字母 答案8
Five letters. Answer: eight.
我不明白
I don't understand. Oh, you
understand all too well, Doctor.
噢 你太明白了 博士
You were to meet Mary Tremlett
Saturday night
at eight o'clock at Bagley Wood
你想趁你太太在唱诗班练唱的时候
在星期六晚上8点和Mary Tremlett
在Bagley Wood见面
while your wife was safely out of
the way at choir practice.
我说不是Bagley Wood
I didn't say Bagley Wood.
至少不是上周六
Not last Saturday anyway.
I said Hinksey.
我说的是Hinksey
而且是6点 不是8点
And it was six o'clock, not eight.
这是下周的谜语
This is next week's puzzle.
下周的?
Next week's?
任何有名气的出谜者
Any setter worth the name...
都会提前为自己准备几个字谜表
will keep a few grids ahead of
himself.
以防生病什么的
Just in case he's taken ill...
这个 你看 Hinksey
Here. You see? Hinksey.
6点 这个字谜表才是我本来要寄的
Six o'clock. This is the grid I meant
to send.
So that's why she didn't turn up.
难怪她没出现
我寄错字谜了
I submitted the wrong puzzle.
Rowan和平时一样 把信封交给我去寄的
Rowan handed me the envelope to post
as usual.
但是有排练的时候 完全忘了
But what with rehearsals,
it completely went out of my mind.
So what happened?
接着呢
到星期三 它还在壁炉架上放着
Oh, come Wednesday,
it was still on the mantelpiece.
And I was about to run it into town
myself
我正要去城里寄的时候
when one of Rowan's students
knocked on the door.
Rowan的一个学生正好过来
A boy called Miles.
一个叫Miles的男孩
Miles Percival?
That's right.
I know him slightly through choir.
是的 我在合唱团和他认识的 不是很熟
Rowan不在 为了少跑一趟
Rowan wasn't in and so to save
myself the trip,
我就问他能不能帮我寄一下信
I asked him if he wouldn't mind
dropping the envelope off.
Did he say what he wanted with your
husband?
他有说来找你先生什么事吗?
我想是学院里的事吧
I assumed it was college business.
But ask him.
I'm sure he'll tell you.
你问他好了 我想他会告诉你的
Miles Percival is dead.
Miles Percival死了
He shot himself.
自杀
That's what I came to
tell your husband the other day.
上次我来找你丈夫就是为了这事
你能描述下星期六晚上Stromming博士的去向吗?
Can you account for Dr Stromming's
whereabouts on Saturday evening?
His whereabouts? He was here.
他的去向? 他在家
Are you sure?
你确定?
每周六晚上你不是要去唱诗班吗?
You have choir practice
every Saturday evening, don't you?
我六点离开的时候他在书房
Well, he was in his study when I
left at six.
我晚上回来的时候他还在那儿
He was still there when I returned
later.
Detective...
What time was that?
- 探...
- 那时几点?
11点左右
Around 11.
After practice, when I came out to
the car, I had a puncture.
排练结束后 我发现车胎破了
And um...
然后...
我只能在那等人来帮忙
I had to wait an age for assistance.
But, please, what is this all about?
可是 请告诉我 为什么要问这个?
我有个问题必须要问 Stromming太太 但是个很敏感的问题
This is a delicate question,
Mrs Stromming... but one I must ask.
你婚姻幸福吗?
Yours is a happy marriage?
- 什么?
- 我是说..
I beg your pardon?
I mean...
You've never had cause
to doubt your husband?
你从没怀疑过你先生吗?
从来没
Never!
Never have I had cause to doubt my
husband, as you put it.
我从没有像你问的这样怀疑我先生
Not for one moment.
从来没有过
I have rehearsals to attend.
我还要去排练
Just tell DCS Crisp what you told me,
all right?
就照你和我说的说给Crisp警司听 知道吗?
You got a minute, sir?
你有时间吗 长官
Stromming计划了整个事件 包括各细节部分
Stromming planned the whole thing,
even down to the last detail.
I believe he even went so far
as to spike his wife's tyre
我认为他甚至戳破他太太的车胎
just to make sure that he got home
before she did.
为的是可以在她回家前赶回来
至今她还认为他整个晚上都在家
So far as she's aware,
he'd been there the whole time.
- 抱歉打断下 长官
- 那...
Sorry to interrupt, sir.
So...
Saturday night he lures
Mary Tremlett to Bagley Wood,
他星期六晚上把Mary Tremlett
诱骗到Bagley Wood
再杀了她
and kills her.
来阻止她说出他们的不正当关系
To stop the truth about their affair
getting out.
And his alibi is what, for the time
in question?
就字谜里的那个时间 他的不在场证明是什么
That he's in Hinksey.
What's he doing in Hinksey?
他在Hinksey 他在Hinksey做什么?
等Mary
Waiting for Mary.
He said that was the intended
rendezvous point for the 12th
他说那本该是他们12日约会的地方
但是他寄错了字谜 把19日的字谜
only he accidentally submitted the
crossword puzzle for the 19th
寄给了牛津日报
to the Oxford Mail.
Anyone see him in Hinksey?
Well, no. He's lying. I know he is.
有人在Hinksey见过他吗? 没 他说谎 我知道他在说谎
What do you think, sir?
你怎么认为 长官
如果Stromming是这个Oz的话
If Stromming is this Oz character...
it stacks up. Bring him in.
说得通 把他带回来问问
Saturday night he killed her,
you say?
你说他星期六晚杀了她的?
那我想你还是等等再下决定 长官
Then I think you probably want to
hang fire, sir.
楼下有个兽医
I've got a vet downstairs
who swears he saw
Mary Tremlett alive and
well, six o'clock...
他说他在星期日早上6点
见过Mary Tremlett
Sunday morning.
我2点左右到的Cherriot农场
I got to Cherriot's Farm round about
two.
臀先露 不是很严重的问题
Breech presentation, which isn't too
much of a problem as a rule.
But the calf managed to get the
umbilical cord around its neck.
但是脐带绕住了小牛的脖子
Hard go of it, I should imagine.
我想 很难弄吧
我想我短时间内都没得玩右旋球了
I doubt I should be bowling leg spin
again for a while.
接生完差不多5点
But all safely delivered round about
five.
I collected my things and headed home
about half past.
我收好东西回家差不多5点半
我刚左转要去Glympton
Anyway, I'd just past the
left turn to Glympton,
and there she was,
waiting at the bus stop.
就看到她等在公车站
- 那时几点
- 噢 6点
What time was this?
Oh, six o'clock.
The Home Service had just come on the
news.
国内新闻刚开始
What did she look like, this girl?
那个姑娘什么样子?
红发 就和报纸上说的一样
Redhead, like it says in the paper.
她穿着的衣服是...
She was wearing some kind of get-up
with a...
I don't know what you call it.
A chevrony-type motif.
我不知道那个叫什么 V型图案
Er, green and white, I think.
哦 绿色和白色
你算错12个小时
You were 12 hours out.
Mary Tremlett不是在星期六晚上
8点16分被杀 而是星期日早上8点16分
It wasn't 8:16 Saturday night Mary
Tremlett was killed, it was 8:16
Sunday morning.
这个兽医看到她在等去Woodstock的头班车
This vet saw her waiting on the
first bus to Woodstock.
- 他可靠吗?
- 没有理由不相信他
Do you believe him?
No reason not to.
他认出了她的衣服
He's identified the dress.
I've just spoken to Mrs Stromming,
sir.
我刚和Stromming太太通过话 长官
8点16分 他们在教堂 两个人都在
8:16, they were in church.
Her and her husband both.
Saint Saviour教堂 牧师已确认
Saint Saviour's. Vicar confirmed.
Which puts Stromming in the clear.
这样Stromming就排除了
He might have had an affair with her
but the rest of it, no-go.
他也许和她有一腿 但不是他杀的
但她是在Bagley Wood被发现的
But she was found in Bagley Wood.
He's put in the wrong puzzle, like
he said.
他寄错字谜了 就像他说的
Mary Tremlett去了那 Stromming没出现
Mary Tremlett goes there,
Stromming never turns up.
那她为什么不回家? 她去哪了?
Then why doesn't she go home?
Where does she go?
Saturday night, until this vet finds
her at the bus stop Sunday morning.
从周六晚上到兽医发现他的周日早上她在哪
我知道说不过去
I didn't say I had it pat.
说不定她遇到了别人
Maybe she met someone.
However you look at it, the long and
the short is we're back to square
one.
不管你怎么认为 我们回到了原点
不一定 长官 尸体边上发现的表
Maybe not, sir.
This watch we found by the body...
It was engraved on the back,
8th October 1964.
背后刻有 1964年10月8日
手表经常当做成年礼的礼物送人
Now, a wristwatch is often given as
a coming-of-age present.
我查过Morse本该在查的自杀案
I checked on that suicide that Morse
is supposed to be dealing with.
Miles Percival.
Yeah?
- Miles Percival
- 怎么
Mary Tremlett's ex-boyfriend.
Mary Tremlett的前男友
她的什么?
Her what?
你不觉得这事应该告诉我们吗?
Don't you think that's something
you might have mentioned?
我排除了 是吗?
I ruled it out.
You did, did you?
Percival's date of birth,
8th October 1943.
Percival的生日是1943年10月8日
他的父母确认我们发现的那个表是去年他们给他的
His parents confirm they gave him a
watch last year matching the one we
found.
Anything else you left off telling
me?
还有什么你没告诉我?
Well, Miles Percival was
the one who delivered
Miles Percival就是那个代Stromming博士
去牛津日报送字谜的人
Dr Stromming's clue set
to the Oxford Mail.
说不定他扫了一眼字谜 长官
Say he took a butcher's at it, sir.
说不定他推测出Stromming和Mary Tremlett
是怎么联系的
Maybe he tumbled onto how Stromming
is making his contacts with Mary
Tremlett.
不会 Miles Percival不懂字谜 他室友告诉我的
No, Percival didn't know the first
thing about crosswords. His flatmate
told me.
Maybe his flatmate doesn't know
Percival as well as he thinks.
说不定他室友不了解Percival
So, what, he's waiting in Bagley
Wood when Mary turns up...
所以是他去Bagley Wood等Mary出现?
Mm-hm. It could be he
was planning on doing
他可能计划杀了他们两个 长官
them both, sir, except
Stromming didn't show.
可是Stromming没出现
They argue, come to blows, even.
That's how he loses his watch.
- 他们发生争执 说不定还动了手
- 所以他才掉了手表
她摆脱他 一直躲到天亮
She gets away from him,
holes up till first
light when she tries to
get the first bus home.
然后想坐头班车回家
但是Percival又找到了她 把她带回Bagley Wood
Only Percival finds her again,
takes her back to Bagley Wood.
Miles Percival还爱着他 长官
Miles Percival was still in love with
her, sir.
他不可能伤害Mary Tremlett
There's no way
that he could harm Mary Tremlett.
Unless it slipped your notice,
Percival blew his brains out.
除非你没注意到Percival给自己脑袋上来了一枪
当然了 因为他发现她死了
Yeah, of course he did,
when he found out she was dead.
- 他接受不了
- 真诗意
It was more than he could stand.
Very poetic.
Except he'd done for himself
before we'd found her body.
除了他在我们发现她尸体前了结了自己
Couldn't have known she was dead,
sir.
他不可能知道她死了 长官
除非他杀了她
Unless he killed her.
Mrs Stromming.
Stromming太太
I feel I should apologise for...
我觉得我该给你道歉
是的
You should.
她是个姑娘 我想你只是尽本分而已
It's a young girl.
I suppose you were doing your job.
A fine mess I made of that.
我搞得一团糟
不过 没事了
Well, that was all.
Morse?
What you asked me about Rowan,
should I have...
你问我关于Rowan的事 我是不是...
Mrs Stromming.
Look, you owe me that at least.
- Stromming太太
- 至少这是你欠我的
Have I been stupid?
我犯傻了吗?
Any stupidity was mine.
只有我在犯傻
警察要做的就是假设 有时候...
It's a policeman's lot to
hypothesise. And sometimes...
Is this your way of saying that you
were wrong?
这是说你的假设是错的?
I suppose it is.
我想是的
抱歉 我只是...
Sorry, I just...
I have been going out of my mind
after what you said.
自从你说了那些之后 我一直心不在焉
不用再想了
Well, think no more of it.
Any man with such a wife as you
would have to be mad to seek
happiness elsewhere.
任何有你这样太太的男人
都不会蠢到去寻花问柳
I don't think Dr Stromming's mad.
我想Stromming不蠢
Look, can I get you a drink?
That's very kind.
- 我能请你喝一杯吗?
- 谢谢
A brandy, then.
一杯白兰地
Someone told Rowan
that you took Greats at Lonsdale.
有人和Rowan说 你以前在Lonsdale读古典人文
Is that true?
真的吗?
算是吧
More or less.
一个读古典人文的怎么会当警察呢?
And how on earth does a Greats man
end up a detective?
我也奇怪
I wonder myself.
I thought perhaps it might be
your father was a policeman.
我想也许因为你父亲也是警察
No, no.
不 不
He was a taxi driver...
before he lost his licence.
他是个出租车司机 后来驾照吊销了
And your mother?
你母亲呢?
她是个桂格教徒
She was raised a Quaker.
Good heavens.
I hope any child of mine might have
老天
more to say about me than,
'She was an Anglican.'
我希望以后我的孩子对我的描述
不只是"她是个圣公会教徒"
她...
She...
噢 我...
Oh, I...
她去世了 那时我12岁
She died... when I was 12.
I shouldn't have asked.
No, not at all.
- 我不该问的
- 不 没事
I'm just afraid that each year,
one's memories, they...
我只是害怕每年 回忆 他们...
But um...
但是...
这么说吧 她在我印象中
Well, let's see, my abiding
impression of her is...
someone soft.
很温柔
香香的头发
The scent of her hair.
Tenderness.
心思敏感
Well...
好了 我还是回去吧
I'd better be getting home.
谢谢
Um, thank you for the...
No, um...
- 为了..
- 不
Thank you for...
Well, just thank you.
谢谢 呃...就是谢谢你
- 那晚安了
- 晚安
Good night, then.
Good night.
Please don't tell my dad. Please.
I won't.
- 请别告诉我爸爸
- 我不会的
He'd kill me if he found out.
I won't say anything. I promise.
- 如果他知道会杀了我的
- 我保证什么都不说
当时你们在哪 Jenny?
Where were you, Jenny?
Mary把我介绍给她认识的这个男人
Mary introduced me to this man she
knew.
他开很多派对
He had these... parties.
A big house at Wolvercote.
在Wolvercote的一个大房子里
我们一开始只以为会很好玩
We thought at first it would be a
giggle.
但其实不是
But it wasn't.
上星期六 Mary在那?
Last Saturday, Mary was there?
我们好几个都去了
There was a few of us went.
Me, Val.
我 Val
但是Mary离开比我们早
Mary left early, though.
Around seven.
7点左右
当时为这事还吵了一架
There was a row over it.
He didn't want her to go.
Who? Who didn't?
他想留住她 谁 谁想留她?
Who threw these parties?
开派对的是谁?
Wait till you get in it.
You've got the leather
你坐进去就知道了
真皮座位 胡桃木仪表板 她真的很棒
seats and the walnut dash.
She's a real beauty.
Oh, hello. Change your mind about
the car?
噢 你好呀 改变主意要买车了?
你知道国家合法年龄是几岁吧 Samuels先生
You aware of the age of consent
in this country, Mr Samuels?
How the law stands in relation to
procuring, say?
再比如跟皮条客有关的法律
Len, could you see to
this lady and gentleman for me?
Len 你能帮我招呼下这两位吗?
先生? 太太?
Sir? Madam?
That's a bloody good sale you've
cost me.
你坏了我好大笔生意
我希望等我结案的时候能让你付出更多
By the time I'm finished
I'll have cost you a great deal more.
Mary Tremlett和其他Cowley Road学校的姑娘
Mary Tremlett was a regular attendee
at your parties,
是你派对常客
along with other girls from Cowley
Road School.
I want the names and addresses of the
men you pimped them to.
我要你给我这些嫖客的姓名和地址
听着 年轻人 你说话注意点
Listen, Sonny Jim,
you want to watch your mouth.
Who do you think you are, coming in
here with talk like that? I won't
have it.
你以为你是谁 跑来说这种话? 我可不接受
I'm a respectable member of the
business community and I'll be
treated as such
我是遵纪守法的好公民 我要求相应的尊重
否则你就准备回去做你的交警吧
or you will find yourself
back on point duty quick as.
现在趁我还没打断你的腿
滚出我的办公室 你个小混帐
Now, get out of my office before I
have someone break your legs, you
little bastard.
滚 滚出去
Go on, get.
你去找Teddy Samuels了
You went to see Teddy Samuels.
Yes, he's running parties out of
some big pile by Wolvercote.
是的 他在Wolvercote那的一栋大房子里开派对
Underage girls.
未成年少女
Mary was there Saturday night.
I don't care where she was Saturday.
- Mary星期六晚上在那
- 我不管她星期六晚上在哪
She was fit and well Sunday morning.
Miles Percival picked her up.
她是星期日早上被Miles Percival杀掉的
是的 但是他这样做很困难不是?
Yes, well, he would have been
hard-pressed to do that, wouldn't
he?
Seeing as he didn't own a car.
鉴于他没车
What the hell do you think you're
about? Pursuing inquiries.
- 你他妈以为你在干什么?
- 查案子
And who gave you leave to do that?
I did.
- 谁允许你这么干的?
- 我
On your way.
去吧
你有什么要说吗 Arthur?
Something you want to say, Arthur?
你知道Teddy勾搭的都是哪些人吗?
You know the kind of people Teddy's
tight with?
I know he's got you in his pocket.
我知道你在他手里
A pony on the first of the month for
turning a blind eye to hooky MOTs is
bad enough
每月1日25镑 无视车辆未年检已经够糟了
but this is the murder of a young
girl.
但这是个年轻姑娘谋杀案
- 不只有我
- 我知道
It's not just me.
Oh, I know.
镇上半数的政要人物都要任Teddy Samuels摆布
Teddy Samuels has got half the brass
in town dancing to his tune.
郡上
In the county.
法官 牧师 议员 同事
Judges, churchmen, councillors,
peers.
你真的以为你有机会和他针锋相对吗 Fred?
You really think you've got a chance
going toe-to-toe with that lot Fred?
我想你还是放几周假吧
I think you should take a couple of
weeks' furlough.
带着Irene开着房车好好认真想想提早退休的事
Run Irene down to the caravan and
have a long, hard think about early
retirement.
You off your nut?
It's that or put in for a transfer.
你疯了? 要么退休要么换部门
Your choice. Either way, don't show
you face in here again.
你自己选 不管你选哪个 别再出现在这里
I'd hate to have to pinch you,
Arthur.
我可不想抓你 Arthur
You wouldn't dare!
你不敢
Who owns it?
It's a murky area.
这房子谁的 难说
So far as I've been able to make out
from the land registry,
目前我从土地登记局只能查到
这地以前是在牛津伯爵的酒店 De Veres名下
the land was owned by the De Veres...
the Earls of Oxford...
后来爵位没了 现在大致算是英国的公有财产
until the title fell dormant. It's
vaguely Crown Estate now.
Crown Estate? That's Treasury,
isn't it? Mm.
公有财产 那是财政部的啊?
Do you want a brew?
要喝一杯吗?
我刚暖好茶壶
I'm just warming the pot.
没牛奶 - 不过有柠檬
There's no milk, I'm afraid.
There's lemon, though.
- 你是谁?
Who the hell are you?
Dempsey. Inspector Thursday,
isn't it?
Dempsey. Thursday督察是吧?
还有Morse探员
And Constable Morse.
破窗而入的是你们吧? 你在这干什么?
That was you putting the windows in,
was it? What's your business here?
Presently a bit of light housework.
正在做些小家务
Defence of the realm is my
bailiwick.
扞卫国家是我的职责
National interest. Pax Britannica
and all that
国家利益 不列颠治下和平 等等
What are you, special branch?
More or less.
你是什么人 政治保安处?
国家利益 不列颠治下和平 等等
Yes, why not?
Get bloody cute and I'll run you in.
算是 好吧 就是 别和我耍着玩 不然把你抓起来
Home Office extension 255.
内政部分机255
Have the duty man put you through to
Colonel Doleman. He'll vouch for my
bona fides.
让值班人员给你接Doleman上校
他可以帮你证实我的好意
No.
不要?
你们是为那个姑娘来的
You're here about the girl.
What do you know about it?
你知道什么?
All you need to know is she left
here alive and well
about seven o'clock on Saturday
evening.
你们只需要知道她星期六晚上7点
从这里出去的时候还活着
Trust me, whoever's killed her is
nothing to do with this.
相信我 杀她的人和这里无关
这到底是哪? 高级妓院
What is this exactly?
Tarts in high places.
皇室不能再有丑闻
HMG won't wear another scandal.
Cliveden的屁股我们还没擦干净呢
We're still going round with a
dustpan and brush after Cliveden.
This is a murder enquiry.
And I hope you catch him.
这是谋杀案调查 我希望你们抓到他
但如果你们抓着这里不放 就等着调离此案吧
But if you keep digging here,
you'll be taken off the case.
国家部门阻挠谋杀案调查
掩藏证据 我很好奇媒体
I wonder what the papers would say
about the Department of State
obstructing a murder enquiry.
Concealing evidence.
会怎么报道这事
Never see light of day.
We'd stick a D notice on it
永不见天日
and you'd be looking at a nice long
stretch for breaching official
secrets.
我们会标记为国防机密
而你们会因泄露国家机密坐很长时间牢
Who are you protecting?
你在保护谁?
I wouldn't be doing my job very well
if I told you, would I?
我告诉你不就失职了吗 你说呢?
Are you sure you won't have a brew?
确定不要来一杯?
Bastards like these,
it's business as usual.
这种混蛋 见得多了
有打手出面挡道 我们就这么让步? 是不是?
So some leg-breaker guards the
stumps and we just walk away?
Is that it?
I want a list of who else
was at this little shindig of yours.
我要出席你这小小狂欢会其他人的名单
你看 督察 我的圈子里
Look, Inspector, I happen to count
a good number of your superior
officers
amongst my close circle. Yeah?
正好有很多你的上司 知道吗?
还是我该说 高层
Or should I say, Square?
I would hate for any of them to be
embarrassed.
我可不想见他们尴尬
Know what I mean?
知道我什么意思吗?
Oh, bugger.
噢 该死
我把烟留车里了
I left my tobacco in the car.
Have a shufti, Morse, would you?
帮我去拿一下好吗 Morse?
现在?
Now?
你那孩子好执着啊
He's a bit keen, your boy, isn't he?
A b it wet behind the ears, though.
但有点天真
要喝什么吗
Want a drink?
Scotch if you've got it.
威士忌
With soda?
要苏打吗?
随便
As it comes.
I've scraped better than you
off the soles of my boots.
我对付过比你更渣的
So get this and get it straight.
所以你听好了
I don't care who you pimp to
or who's pal you are down the Lodge.
我不管你给谁拉客 和谁关系好
You try and come it with me,
I'll break you.
和我玩试试 揍不死你
Was in my pocket all along.
一直在我口袋里
Mr Samuels has come over with a
nosebleed.
Samuels先生流鼻血了
我告诉他头要往后仰
I told him to keep his head back.
We all done, then, Teddy?
You've made a big mistake.
- 我们完事了是吧 Teddy?
- 你犯了个大错
那你也错了 手帕留着吧
Then that makes two of us.
You can keep the hanky.
Sir...
Save your breath.
- 长官...
- 少说两句
我绕了大半个地球可不是为了把敌人赶走
I didn't march half way across the
world to put Jerry back in his box
然后让这些衣冠禽兽横行霸道的
for jumped-up spivs
to end up running the show at home.
What about the law?
那法律呢?
法律有对有错
There's right and there's wrong.
我知道我站哪边
I know which side I'm on.
是吗?
Do you?
I don't care how much. I'm not
interested. I think you will be.
- 我不想知道有多少 我不感兴趣
- 我想你会感兴趣的
我奇怪了很久 为什么没人动Samuels
I wondered for a while why no-one
was willing to go after a crook like
Samuels.
特别是Crisp
Especially Crisp.
你可以事先和我说的
Well, you might have told me.
我不知道警局里谁可以信任 更别说陌生人
I didn't know who I could trust in
my own nick, never mind a stranger.
You think Teddy Samuels killed Mary
Tremlett?
你觉得Teddy Samuels杀了Mary Tremlett?
或知道谁干的
Or knows who did.
Inspector Thursday in yet?
Gone to see the Tremletts.
Thursday督察回来了吗? 去Tremlett家了
你了解女人的衣服吗?
Do you know much about women's
clothes?
Besides they look better off than
on? Why?
除了它们脱了比穿上好看? 怎么
Something someone said.
有人说过什么
I was trying to remember.
我想不起来
Morse?
Detective Chief Superintendent Crisp
wants you.
警司找你
Morse
Morse.
丰乳肥臀
Odalisque.
Oda what?
丰什么?
What's that mean, then?
Someone like Jenkins there.
- 那是什么意思?
- 跟Jenkins一样
What, Welsh?
什么 威尔士人?
养着 为了娱乐
Fed. For pleasure.
Is it true?
是真的吗?
我建议你 考虑清楚再回答
I'd advise you to consider
very carefully before you answer.
这是非常严重的投诉
This is a very serious complaint.
Thursday督察是不是打了Teddy Samuels?
Did Inspector Thursday hit Teddy
Samuels?
没有 长官
No, sir.
Right, clear your desk. I want you
on the next train to Carshall bloody
Newtown
好 收拾你的桌子
我要你马上滚回Carshall Newtown
或哪来滚哪去
or wherever it is you came from.
I've no use for troublemakers.
我这里不要惹麻烦的人
My letter of resignation.
It's been burning a hole
in my pocket this past week.
我的辞呈 已经在口袋里放了一个星期了
Perhaps you'll see it reaches
the appropriate channels. Get out!
或许你能看到它经适当途径呈上
Flunk out again, have you... college?
又糗了吧 大学生
I read your file, boy.
我看过你档案了
Three years Lonsdale.
在Lonsdale读了3年
Threw the towel in before your
finals.
最后关头承认失败
That's the trouble with you poshos.
No gumption.
你们这种上层人的毛病 没胆量
一遇到困难就夹着尾巴回家找妈妈
First sign of bother, it's off back
home to Mummy, tail between.
别难过
Mm, no hard feelings!
You've done me a favour.
你帮了我忙呢
Pastures new.
新工作 扫黄组
烟雾缭绕
Vice in the smoke.
And you on the slow boat to China.
而你 长路漫漫啊
你打算怎么办?
What will you do?
祷告?
Praise the God of all.
Drink the wine, and beer.
喝酒
世界照样转
And let the world be the world.
Another?
No, got to mind the shop.
再来杯? 不了 还要做事
Did you ever make any headway
with what was on the back of her
hand?
她手背上那个字查得怎么样了?
What was it, FLA...?
那个什么 FLA?
17B.
17B
Or 178.
要么178
我们试过找车辆登记FLA178 但是没发现
We tried it as a vehicle
registration,
FLA 178, but nothing doing.
And if it was Flat 17B...
如果是房间号17B的话...
There was something missing off the
end, though.
但是那后面还写着什么
Another letter or number, I think.
Maybe. It's hard to say.
- 另个字母或者数字 我觉得
- 大概吧 很难说
Why?
What? Oh, just, well...
为什么 什么? 噢 只是...
没什么 没事
Nothing. Doesn't matter.
Well...
It's no longer my concern.
- 呃...
- 不关我的事了
Can you tell Thursday, if he wants
to know who killed Mary Tremlett
你能告诉Thursday
如果他想知道谁杀了Mary Tremlett
find out where her clothes came
from.
就去查查她的衣服是哪来的
Did Mary ever mention a Teddy
Samuels?
Mary提过一个叫Teddy Samuels的人吗?
在Park Town那开修车厂的
Runs a garage round the back of
Park Town.
It's not a name I've heard her
mention.
没听她提过
Have you?
你呢?
她被人抓到和这个男人在一起是吧?
She's got herself caught up with this
bloke, then, has she?
我们只是想了解任何她通过他认识的人
It's just we're interested in anyone
she may have known through him.
She ever go to Wolvercote,
so far as you know?
你们知道她去过Wolvercote吗?
Oh. I'm afraid Rowan's not in.
噢 Rowan不在家
It's you I came to see.
我来找你的
我想在走前 来说声再见
I wanted to say goodbye.
Before I push off.
You're leaving Oxford?
Oxford. The police. All of it.
你要离开牛津? 牛津 警局 所有的
You'd better come in.
进来吧
I took the liberty...
我冒昧...
It seemed too good an opportunity to
let pass.
这机会太难得 我不能错过
能遇到心目中的女英雄机会可不多
It's seldom one gets to meet one's
heroines.
女英雄? 才不是
Heroine? Surely not?
真的 你都不知道
Yeah, more than you could know.
你拯救了我
You saved my life.
- 太诡异了吧
- 真的
What an extraordinary thing to say.
It's true, nevertheless.
我是在一个灰色 没有知觉的地方长大的
The place that I grew up
was a grey, unfeeling nothing.
Then one day I heard your voice.
有一天 我听到了你的歌声
And... And I knew for the first time
that there was...
然后 然后那是我第一次知道 世界上还是有...
美丽地方的
beauty in the world.
Would you sign it?
你能给我签个名吗?
对我真的很有意义
It would mean a great deal.
Yes.
当然
天呐 看看我
Oh, heavens, look at me.
我有
I have.
Often.
一直看你
Are you flirting with me?
你在和我调情吗?
A little.
大概
有一点
Perhaps.
你不可以
You mustn't.
I love my husband.
我爱我的丈夫
很爱
Very much.
I know.
我知道
我要写什么呢?
What shall I put?
Samuels的保险不合法律规范
Samuels' insurance against police
interest.
Wicked thing, blackmail.
做坏事 勒索
God knows I'd have done the same
if it had been my daughter.
天知道如果是我女儿的话 我也会这么做
I burnt the negatives. All of them.
见不得人的照片都被我烧了
Jenny doesn't have to worry any
more. And nor do you.
Jenny不需要再担心了 你也是
长官
Sir.
还有谁知道?
Who else knows?
你 我和Morse
Between you, me and Morse.
You can rely on his discretion.
He's a good lad.
你可以信任他的判断力 他是个好孩子
如果不是他一直查这么紧 我们没法查到这里
We wouldn't be where we are now
if he hadn't kept pushing.
Sharon!
Sharon...
谢谢你的咖啡 还有...
Well, thank you for the coffee
and...
You know, you should find yourself
a girl.
你知道吗 你该找个女朋友
I did once.
找过一次
We were engaged.
What happened?
我们订婚了 后来呢?
噢 她以前的男朋友
Oh... someone she'd left behind.
They'd been something in their first
year and after then she took up with
me.
他们在一起的第一年发生了什么 然后她就和我在一起
But not to be.
但没有发生什么
别难过
I'm sorry.
真的
Truly.
Perhaps better to have loved
and lost.
也许经历过爱过失去过才好
So I'm told.
别人是这么和我说的
再见 Stromming太太
Well, goodbye, Mrs Stromming.
Yours, I believe.
我相信这是你的
有新进展
There's been a development.
He had to pay.
他要付出代价
为了Mary
For Mary.
I mean, I knew he was bad but...
我是说 我知道他坏 但是...
我从没想过..
I never thought...
His own daughter.
他自己的女儿
我们的女儿
Our daughter.
你和Teddy Samuels?
You and Teddy Samuels?
Summer, '49.
她叫Summer 49年生
Mum and Dad said I shouldn't have
my life ruined with a kiddie so
young.
爸妈说我的生活不该被这么小个孩子给毁了
所以他们帮你带
So they took her on.
Teddy didn't want anything to do with
it.
Teddy不想和她扯上关系
威胁我不许告诉别人
Threatened me if I told anyone.
And then you come round.
然后你来家里
Just hearing his name...
光听到他名字
我就控制不住
something went in me.
这些年来
All these years.
The thought of him
having anything to do with Mary.
一想到他对Mary做的事
我不后悔
I'm not sorry.
It's a rum go, Morse, and no
mistake.
这真是件怪事 Morse
Families, shame...
这家人让人羞愧
投错胎难道是孩子的错吗?
How is it any fault of a kiddie
whatsoever the sheets it's born?
Her flesh and blood and yet all
this,
自己的骨肉还能这样对待
搞得好像我们不是父母生的一样
as if we didn't all get here the
same way.
那是行不通的 我知道 铁定不行
It won't do, I know that much.
It won't bloody do.
Mary Tremlett的衣服怎么了
What's all this business
with Mary Tremlett's outfit?
噢 Mary Tremlett的胸围36C
Oh, well, Mary Tremlett took a size
36C in a bra
but the dress found with her body
was a size small.
但是发现她尸体的时候 她穿的是小号
She couldn't have squeezed into that
outfit if her life depended on it.
她要是还想活命的话 绝对不会穿这么小的
Bought by an admirer?
That was my thinking.
- 喜欢她的人送的?
- 我也这么想过
说到女人衣服尺寸 我是说...
When it comes to women's dress sizes,
I mean...
让McLeash去列个当地零售商的名单
Have McLeash run down a list of
local stockists.
同时我们最好去和我们的朋友Teddy谈谈
In the meantime, we'd better have a
word with friend Teddy.
He might be in more of a mood
to make himself useful this morning.
说不定他今天心情好 能更有用些
It's Morse.
是我 Morse
I'm in hospital with Inspector
Thursday.
我和Thursday督察在医院
Any luck with the outfitters?
卖衣服的查到什么吗?
噢 好吧 继续找
Oh, well, keep trying.
The pips have gone. I'm out of
change.
噢 该死 没硬币 电话要断了
你能打回给我吗? 电话是270 Otmoor 两个O
Can you call me back?
The number's Otmoor 2270. Otmoor.
O-T-M...
O T M...
Yes, straight away.
There's something I need to check.
是的 直接去 有件事我要查查
She's done a proper job on him.
If he pulls
她下手真狠
如果他能救回来的话 多半也是个植物人
through, the doctor says
he's likely a vegetable.
How did you make out?
Percival's in the clear.
- 你查得怎么样
- Percival排除嫌疑
他不仅没车
Not only did he not have
access to a vehicle but,
而且根据Lomax所说
他不会开车
according to Lomax, he
couldn't even drive.
That's not all.
What?
- 不光这些
- 什么?
You remember what was written
on the back of Mary's hand?
你还记得Mary Tremlett手背上的字吗
FLA178.
A car reg, yeah. Nothing doing.
FLA178 车牌啊 查不到
It wasn't a car reg or part of an
address or anything of the sort.
因为它不是车牌也不是地址
FLA is an abbreviation of FLAxman,
FLA是FLAxman的缩写
是一个覆盖切尔西地区的伦敦电话局
which is a London telephone exchange
covering the Chelsea area.
FLA178? You're a digit short.
- FLA178? 那还少了一位
I got McLeash to check all 10
possibilities.
- 我要McLeash查了1到10
FLAxman 1788是Richard Lovell爵士家里的电话
FLAxman 1788 is the number of the
London home of Sir Richard Lovell,
外事大臣 也是北牛津地区议员
Minister for Overseas Affairs
and constituency MP for Oxford North.
You talk to him?
His housekeeper.
- 你和他通过话?
- 他的管家
Lovell was in Oxford last weekend
from Friday to Sunday.
Lovell上周五到周日在牛津
He has a house by Woodstock
called Applegate.
他在Woodstock有栋大房子 叫Applegate
Detective Inspector Thursday, sir.
Thursday督察 爵士
Detective Constable Morse.
Morse探员
有时间聊一聊吗?
Wonder if we might speak to you
a moment?
With me?
和我?
当然 请进
Certainly. Please.
有什么可以帮你们的?
So, what can I do for you?
I'm hoping you'll be able to tell us
how your London telephone number
我希望你可以告诉我们 你伦敦家里的电话号码
came to be found
written on the hand of a schoolgirl
是如何出现在一个上周日在Bagley Wood
murdered last Sunday in Bagley Wood.
被谋杀的女学生的手背上的
My telephone number?
我的电话号码
FLAxman 1788.
FLAxman 1788
是你的电话吧?
That is your phone number?
是的 但是...
Yes, it is. But...
我不知道为什么这个年轻姑娘
会有我的电话号码
how this young girl came to have it,
I'm afraid I haven't the foggiest.
Her name was Mary Tremlett.
她叫Mary Tremlett
A redhead.
红头发
One of the young girls you'll have
met at Teddy Samuels' parties.
是你上周六参加Teddy Samuels
在Wolvercote的派对上
You attended one last Saturday at
Wolvercote.
见过的其中一位姑娘
我不认识
I don't think so.
It sounds most unsavoury.
没听说过
可惜 可惜
Dear, dear.
"可惜 可惜"? 一个年轻姑娘被勒死
脱光了留树林里
'Dear, dear'? A young girl strangled
and left naked in the woods
你能说的只是"可惜 可惜"?
and all you can say is 'dear, dear'?
Morse.
Morse
你否认当时在那儿是吗 大臣
Do you deny you were there, Minister?
自然
Naturally.
除非你有证据
And unless you have evidence to the
cobtrary...
我想 谈话到此为止吧
I'm afraid this meeting
is at an end.
这就是Dempsey要矢口否认的
I think we can say who Dempsey's
looking out for, don't you?
A minister of the Crown.
这就是内阁阁员?
Need more than a phone number
to make it stick.
光有电话号码还不够
除非... 她的衣服
Unless... Her outfit.
If Lovell was this secret admirer
and we can find who sold it to him...
如果是Lovell送给她的这件衣服
我们可以找到卖衣服给他的人
可以把他和Mary Tremlett联系在一起
We can tie him to Mary Tremlett.
McLeash查到商店名单了吗? 嗯 应该查到了
McLeash come through with that list
of stockists? Yeah, should have.
You get onto that, I'll put Crisp in
the picture.
你去查查衣服 我去给Crisp汇报
You tried the outfit girl?
你找到卖衣服的人了?
那他跑不了了
Then we've got him.
What?
怎么?
Whelks.
海螺
Mary Tremlett最后吃的东西
Mary Tremlett's last meal.
Eaten an hour or so before she died.
在她死前1小时左右吃的
我早餐不会吃这些
That's not my idea of breakfast.
Is it yours?
你会吗?
What are you saying?
She didn't die Sunday morning?
你想说什么? 她不是星期日早上死的?
But the vet saw her at the bus stop.
但是兽医有在公车站看到她
Well, yes.
是的
也不全是
And no.
不管是不是 都不是Lovell杀的
Either way, it wasn't Lovell who
killed her.
The awful thing is, it all started as
a joke.
最可怕的是 这都只因一个笑话而起
A wager between two fools
who should have known better.
两个蠢货的一个赌注 ??
- 赌多少?
- 5镑
How much?
Five pounds.
来吧
You're on.
Flattered by Stromming's
attentions, perhaps
Mary Tremlett很高兴得到Stromming的注意
even believing herself
to be in love with him,
也许还认为爱上他
她奋不顾身地投入了进去
Mary Tremlett threw herself into
their affair,
abandoning the young man with whom
she had hitherto been close.
抛弃了一直和她很要好的年轻人
Distraught, Miles Percival confided
his fears
烦恼的Miles Percival向另一位
他觉得可以让Stromming收手的人
吐露了他的担心
to the one person he thought might be
able to bring Stromming to heel.
Stromming太太 我们能借一步说话吗?
Mrs Stromming, can we have a word?
I doubt that she believed him.
我觉得她不相信他
但是慢慢地她意识到了真相
But gradually she came to realise the
truth.
为了不和她丈夫正面冲突而可能会失去他
Rather than confront her husband
and risk losing him for ever,
another idea took hold of her mind.
她想到了另外一个办法
So she began.
然后她行动了
# Un bel di from Madame Butterfly #
Have a wonderful day.
一天愉快
The substitution of the puzzle
was the easiest part.
寄谜语是最简单的部分
What she really needed
was someone to take the blame.
但她需要的是有人背这个黑锅
She already had the perfect
candidate.
她已经有一个完美人选
帮我送下这个好吗?
Drop that in for me, will you?
- 好的
- 谢谢
Sure.
Thank you.
其他和她计划的一样
The rest fell out exactly as she
planned.
On Saturday evening,
星期六晚上
Mary Tremlett left Samuels's party
for Bagley Wood,
Mary Tremlett离开Samuels的派对
去Bagley Wood等她的爱人
expecting to meet her lover.
只不过发现她等来的不是Stromming博士
Only, it wasn't Dr Stromming she
found waiting.
Mary Mary!
Mary. Mary!
I believe Rosalind Stromming
was waiting for her with some kind of
crowbar.
我相信Rosalind Stromming等她的时候
带的是铁橇之类的
She stripped Mary Tremlett and left
a green and white party dress by her
body,
她脱了Mary Tremlett的衣服
留下了另一条白绿相间的裙子
a dress rather than the dress.
在她尸体边上
有两裙子
There were two.
第二天早上任何路过车站的人
The following morning
anyone passing the bus stop
would have seen exactly
what Rosalind Stromming wanted them
to see,
都能看到Rosalind Stromming想让他们看到的
a redhead in a green, black and white
chevron print dress.
一个红头发姑娘 穿着从Mary Tremlett身上脱下来
To be taken from Mary Tremlett.
带V字图案白绿相间的裙子
假发和裙子我估计是找不到了
The wig and dress I doubt we'll ever
find.
接着就是最后一幕
The stage was set for the final act.
所有剩下的都为了向警方指明杀害Mary的凶手
All that remained was to provide the
police with Mary's murderer.
It was the perfect crime,
in all respects. Bar one.
从各方面来说 这都是完美犯罪
It was essential to her plan that the
two dresses appear identical.
除了一点
But what she failed to
take into account was the
她计划中最重要的是
两条裙子必须要好认
但是她没想到她比Mary要小两号
fact that she is two
sizes smaller than Mary.
The shop girl remembered at once.
商店的女孩马上就记起了她
那位戴着钻石耳环的女士
The beautiful woman with the diamond
earrings.
# Un bel di from Madame Butterfly #
Bravo.
唱得好
Bravissimo.
唱太好了
Divina.
Divina
什么事?
So, what's this about?
Your decision to retire from Her
Majesty's Government and retire from
public life.
你决定退休 从政府和公众面前消失
My what?
我什么?
我们觉得用健康问题做理由较合适
省得大家难堪
We thought grounds of ill health.
Spare everyone's blushes.
She was 15... Dickie.
她15岁...色鬼
只不过是些无伤大雅的... 娱乐?
It was just a bit of harmless...
Fun?
A schoolgirl coerced into bed round
from one dirty old sod to another
一个女学生被一群下流的老混蛋轮奸
like the Sunday sprouts, 'fun'?
娱乐?
For you and your mates, maybe.
对你和你同伙来说 也许是
This is ridiculous.
Ridiculous.
这太荒唐 荒唐
一个政府大臣开性派对
A government minister at a sex party.
Writing his telephone number on the
hand of a teenage girl.
还把他的电话号码写在小姑娘的手上
Now, THAT'S ridiculous.
这才叫荒唐
我们暂时没把你的名字曝光
We've kept your name out of it.
So far.
但是有个小警察一直在查 而且他不肯放弃
But there's a young copper chasing
this and he's not so willing to play
the game.
Morse?
和他解释解释 噢 我试过了
Explain to him.
Oh, I've tried.
Not for sale.
没用
You do the decent thing, his guv'nor
might be able to rein him in.
你照我说的做 他老大说不定能压住他
We'll see what Harold has to say
about it.
我要听听Harold对这件事怎么说
This is what he has to say about it.
这就是他要说的
两个办法 答应退休或是要我动手?
There's two ways out. This one... or
do I have to get blood on my shoes?
What time's your train?
你的火车几点?
It's quarter past.
15分的车
睡了没?
Sleep?
如果我能早点想到...
If I'd have worked things through
sooner...
If I'd have realised...
Stop.
- 如果我知道...
- 好了
The 'if' game's no good to any
bugger.
"如果"游戏可没什么好处
You keep on, it'll drive you round
the twist.
你越想只会越纠结
I know.
我知道
Rosalind Stromming was dead from the
moment she decided to kill an
innocent girl.
不管Rosalind Stromming以前有多好
从她决定杀死一个无辜姑娘的那一刻起
Or dying, at least, inside.
她就已经死了 至少 内心里
Whatever was good of her.
好的本性已经死了
走吧
Come on, then.
If you're going to make that
train...
如果你还想赶上火车...
Mind if I drive?
可以让我开车吗?
Carshall Newtown,
that really what you want?
你真的想待在Carshall Newtown?
I don't know.
我不知道
I was thinking I might pack it
all in.
我在想重新开始
Pick up my degree.
把学历读完
The world's long on academics,
Morse, but woeful short of good
detectives.
学海无崖 Morse 但是好侦探真的很少
Things as they are,
I could use a permanent back man.
事实上 我还真的需要一个好助手
I mean, we did pretty well
this time out.
我是说 我们这次合作得很不错啊
Give or take.
总体来说
I'd see you right, of course,
make sure we get you through your
sergeant's exam, eh?
当然 我会满足你的要求
但是你得通过警长考试
有了真正的鼓励 谁知道呢
With the proper encouragement,
who knows?
What you've got to ask is, where do
you see yourself in 20 years?
你要问自己的是 你觉得20年后你是什么样的
Morse?
Endeavour.
Endeavour
Subtitles by ITFC, MemoryOnSmells
http://uksubtitles.tumblr.com